<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Anaconda_Addon_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<article>
    <xi:include href="Article_Info.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    <section id="section_introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>
        What is Anaconda? What is it supposed to do and be? Why has addons
        support been added with the rewrite?  What is Initial Setup? How to
        write addons for the Initial Setup?
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="section_architecture">
      <title>Architecture</title>
      <para>
        How does Anaconda look internally? Which modules Anaconda uses/consists
        of? How and where does Anaconda store data?
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Hub&amp;Spoke model</title>
      <para>
        What is the Anaconda's basic UI model? Why this model? Pros and cons of
        the model. What elements Anaconda's UI consists of? How does the UI work
        with the installation data? How this works in text mode?
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Threads and communication</title>
      <para>
        Why is Anaconda multi-thread? What should be run in a separate thread?
        How does internal communication work? What are the dangerous actions
        with threads and Gtk and what Anaconda provides to overcome them?
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Addon structure</title>
      <para>
        What is the basic structure of an Anaconda addon? Which parts it has to
        define and which are optional?
     </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Writing an Anaconda addon</title>
      <para>
        Which packages are needed? Hello world addon example built step by step
        with comments and API description. Coding style. Comments on the
        "advanced features" provided by Anaconda.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deploying and testing an Anaconda addon</title>
      <para>
        How to deploy and test an Anaconda addon? On the running system vs. with
        the installation image. How should be an addon delivered? Packaging and
        basic structure for the .spec file.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Addons welcomed</title>
      <para>
        Where to find help with the development? Additional documentation and
        referential addon implementations? FAQ. Few words to encourage.
      </para>
    </section>

    <xi:include href="Revision_History.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    <index />
</article>

